<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Irish massacre; or A true narrative of the unparallel'd cruelties exercised in Ireland upon the Brittish Protestants, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E353_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861649</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113789</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113789)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E353[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Irish massacre; or A true narrative of the unparallel'd cruelties exercised in Ireland upon the Brittish Protestants, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Parker by Thomason.</note>
                  <note>Listed in Thomason Catalogue under Sept. 1646.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Hen. Parker Esqr.; begun before he went over to Hambor; but not finished".</note>
                  <note>A fragment; first leaf signed: B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113789:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113789:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE IRISH MASSACRE; <hi>OR</hi> A true Narative of the Unparallell'd Cruelties exerciſed in IRELAND upon the BRITTISH Proteſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat cauſeleſſe Antipathy which uſes to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unavoidable endleſſe matter of diſpute betwixt Magiſtracy and Populacy, betwixt thoſe which command, and thoſe which obey, hath in all ages and countries proved fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and productive of ſad events. This is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted almoſt by all Polititians (being no other commonly then Court Paraſites) to the fault of thoſe many, whoſe lot it is to be ſubjected to government, upon pretence that theſe never think their liberty looſe enough; but for my part my reaſon rather leades me to impute the fault hereof to thoſe few, which are intruſted with government, foraſmuch as theſe ſcarce ever thinke their authority full enough. For that end which the diffuſive body of the people aimes at is probably its owne weale, and this is no improper or juſt end, nor is it at all inconſiſtent with the true weale and happineſſe of thoſe, which are placed above them: but that good which Commanders in cheefe aime at, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times extends no further then to their owne perſons, or families, and this ever remaines improper, or unjuſt, becauſe it cannot ſtand with the welfare of thoſe which are placed below them. Irrationall creatures by inſtinct of Nature are directed to that which is their peculiar good: wherefore if we degrade the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to a brutiſh condition, if we deny them reaſon, and if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of multitude, wee comprehend alſo all that are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113789:2"/> not inveſted with ſupreame power: yet unleſſe we will deny them naturall inſtinct too, we cannot ſuppoſe them utterly unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of that benefit and aſſurance which a well tempered po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecy holds forth to them. And if the groſſe number be not held ſo intelligent, as authority makes thoſe which ſit at the Sterne, yet this hinders not, but that the groſſe number may act as regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and purſue as juſt ends, as thoſe which are deeper read in poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. And as for ſtory, and antiquity, in all my reading I could never yet finde one precedent, where the generality of a State convened or repreſented in an orderly forme, did unjuſtly quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell or unlawfully capitulate with their Lords, but the contrary is moſt remarkeable every where, <hi>Quicquid delirant reges, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe Civill warres, which now infeſt <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> much hath beene pleaded in behalfe of the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and much Rhetorick hath beene uſed to lay the blame upon the Subjects diſloyalty, and ſome thinke that in this warre there is an intervention of ſome new matter, never before prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented or paralleld in any Age. But in my conceite, the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſe which imbroyles us all, is the ſame pretence of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity, which hath always produced the like effects elſe where, and though the King ſeeme to diſowne the Iriſh, as not Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to his purpoſe, and the Iriſh diſownes us, as not concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with their projections; yet ſtill there is no Novelty in the buſineſſe, beſides a more artificiall and darke diſguiſe, then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly peeces of this nature have been covered with. Diverſity of Religions hath beene a wicked meanes to heighten enmitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our Nations, and is become an expedient which the Court makes great uſe of for a vizard to its deſignes; but diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Religions hath beene long favoured at Court, and therefore we may conclude it is but ſubordinate to that cauſe for which it was ſo favoured. The Iriſh now murder us for aſpiring to that liberty, which they themſelves claime with leſſe moderation then we doe, not that they thinke us enemies to their liberty but to their Religton, nor becauſe they are enemies in truth to our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie but to our Religion. Nevertheleſſe Religion, as Religion is not the ſupreame motive, or incentive of the Iriſh n this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feude: for the true Religion (which is but one and contented with a ſmall traine) may be loved for it ſelfe, by ſuch as are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly zelots to it; whereas all falſe religions, and all falſe profeſſors
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113789:2"/> of the true Religion have other ingagements then meere conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. To paſſe by the vulgar therefore or common herd of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which are but paſſive, as the waves are under the winds, and which doe but borrow Religion from education meerely, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally are moſt docile in that religion which is accompanied with the greateſt preſent temporall emoluments: if we looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the primary active party in <hi>Ireland</hi> (whatſoever their nugato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſimulatory pretexts were, for the Kings Prerogative) the true intent of their inſurrection was the inlargement of the Romiſh faith, and their zeale to that faith was onely inflamed by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny civill advantages which ſeemed attendant upon it. Popery hath now long ſince beene diſcovered to be an impoſture or nothing elſe but a ſlie ſophiſme, to eſtabliſh Empire in the long Robe, and wreſt it from ſuch as they account ſecular men, and as the Preiſts and Jeſuits have beene the maine Incendiaries in all our differences, ſo we well enough know what their particular Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt was therein.</p>
            <p>Tis ſtrange that any Princes, eſpecially ſuch as are capacious, and intelligent ſhould think it any addition of Royallty to them in the State to admit of a Superiour in the Church, and to ſtoop to any rivallity of dominion (though diſtinguiſht, and blancht over with the Epithite of ſpirituall) but tis more prodigious in Proteſtant Princes. Yet we muſt take notice Popery is an intox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icating potion mingled with all the force and skill of Magick, and as it ſometimes ſoothes and ſmoothes the people by curbing Princes for the Churches better accomodation, ſo alſo at other times and moſt conſtantly it ſaddles and bridles the people for both Preiſts and Princes ſatisfaction. And leaſt proteſtant Princes ſhould wholy abominate it, as adverſe to their Grandour, with extraordinary profeſſions of devotion to them it labours to infuſe and inſinuate theſe fragments of <hi>Machavell.</hi> Firſt, that Subjects in generall are enemies to Authority, nay the cheifeſt enemies that they ought to countermine and plot againſt. Secondly, that this enmity is beſt broken by breeding, and maintaining diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Then having laid theſe grounds, its next ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are, firſt that of all Subjects none are particularly ſo malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Royallty as Proteſtants, and of all Proteſtants the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh hold their Kings to the moſt narrow limits.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that none are ſo fit to be oppoſed to <hi>Britiſh</hi> Proteſtants
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113789:3"/> herein, as thoſe which are the profeſt Vaſſalls of the Sea of Rome: and are now in a ſtate of perſecution. How far theſe poyſonous, curſed ſuggeſtions have prevailed with our King, may be read in characters of bloud all over our three Nations, and it is my intent at this time more fully to relate. The Iriſh Rebellion which with ſo much horrid fury, &amp; ſlaughter broke forth upon the 23 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1641. is my maine ſubject, and I doubt not but that (diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as it is already, though very much of it remaine as yet in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, in regard that the Court ever ſtood as in the darke to us, whilſt we are placed in the light to the Court) will ſufficiently ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie that the prime Engeniers and Maſters of this infernall plot had not religious but politick ends therein, and thoſe not peculiar to <hi>Ireland,</hi> but common to all the three Kingdomes, and ſuch as I have already intimated. But I muſt not frame a meere narrative, or play the Hiſtorian, I have to doe with a ſhameles and lying ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, with whom Authorities themſelves are ſcarce authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: wherefore for my cheife fundamentall, I will inſiſt upon that confeſſion which was made, and penned by the Lord <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queir</hi> himſelf. This confeſſion was voluntarily written by the ſaid Lord about <hi>June,</hi> 1642. whilſt he was a priſoner in the Tower, and it was afterwards avowed by him at the day of his death in the preſence of the Leiutenant of the Tower &amp; of the two Sheriffes of <hi>London,</hi> and many others. And becauſe it ſeemes ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in ſome paſſages, and a little too darke in others, and hitherto hath not beene printed in ſo exact a Coppy as it might, I ſhall now publiſh it, more perfect, and more punctually agreeing with the originall, (which ſtill remaines in Maſter <hi>Becks</hi> hands of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnes Inne</hi>) and for the better underſtanding of ſuch as are not ſo inquiſitive, or inſpective I ſhall adde ſome Obſervations, and give a few unqueſtionable Illuſtrations of mine owne.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Confeſſion followes <hi>in haec verba.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label>JUNE 1642.</label> BEing in <hi>Dublin</hi> Candlemas Terme laſt was twelve moneth, the Parliament then ſitting, Maſter <hi>Roger More</hi> did write to me deſiring me that if I could in that ſpare time I would come to his houſe (for then the Parliament did nothing but ſit and adjourn, expecting a commiſſion for the continuance thereof, their former commiſſion being expired) and that ſome things he had to ſay to me, that did neerely concerne me, and on receipt of his Letter, the new Commiſſion for continuing the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113789:3"/> Parliament landed, and I did returne him an anſwer that I could not fulfill his requeſt for that preſent, and thereupon he himſelfe came to towne preſently after, and ſending to me, I went to ſee him to his lodging, and after ſome little time ſpent in ſalutations, he began to diſcourſe of the many afflictions and ſufferings, of the Natives of that Kingdom, and particularly in thoſe latter times of my Lord of <hi>Straffords</hi> Government (which gave diſtaſt to the whole Kingdom) and then he began to particularize the ſuffering of them that were the more ancient Natives, as were the Iriſh, how that on the ſeverall Plantations they were all put out of their Anceſtours eſtates; which ſufferings as he ſaid did beget a generall diſcontentment over all the whole Kingdome in both the Natives; to wit, the old and new Iriſh, and that if the Gentlemen of the Kingdom were diſpoſed to free themſelves furtherly from the like inconveniency, and get good conditions for themſelves for regaining their Anceſtours (or at leaſt a good part thereof) eſtates, they could never deſire a more convenienter time, then that time, (the diſtempers of <hi>Scotland</hi> being then a foot) and did aske me what I thought of it. I made him anſwer that I could not tell what to think of it, ſuch matters being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether out of my element, then he would needs have an oath of ſecrecie from me, which I gave him, and thereupon he told me that he ſpoke to the beſt Gentlemen of quality in <hi>Lemſter,</hi> and a great part of <hi>Conaught</hi> touching that matter, and he found all of them willing thereunto, if ſo be they could draw to them the Gentlemen of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> for which cauſe ſaid he, I came to ſpeake to you; then he began to lay down to me the caſe that I was in then, overwhelmed in debt, the ſmalneſſe of my eſtate, and the greatneſſe of the eſtate my Anceſtors had, and how I ſhould be ſure to get it againe, or at leaſt a good part thereof, and moreover how the welfare and mainteining of the Catholique Religion, which (he ſaid) undoubtedly the Parliament now in <hi>England</hi> will ſuppreſſe) doth depend on it, for ſaid he it is to be feared, and ſo much I heare from every underſtanding man, the Parliament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the utter ſubverſion of our Religion; by which perſwaſions he obtained my conſent, and ſo demanded whether any more of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> Gentlemen were in Town, I told him that Maſter <hi>Philip Rely,</hi> Maſter <hi>Torrilagh O Neile,</hi> brother to Sir <hi>Phillim O Neile,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Colloe Macmahone</hi> were in town, and ſo for that time wee parted.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113789:4"/>
               <p>The next day he invited Maſter <hi>O Rely</hi> and me to dine with him, and after dinner, he ſent for thoſe other Gentlemen Mr. <hi>Neale,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Macmahon,</hi> and when they were come, he began the diſcourſe formerly uſed to me, to them, and with the ſame perſwaſions formerly uſed to me, he obtained their conſent, And then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſcourſe of the feazebility and eaſines of the attempt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering matters as they then ſtood in <hi>England,</hi> the troubles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the great number of able men in the Kingdome (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ireland</hi>) what ſuccours they were (more then) to hope for, from abroade, and the Army then raiſed all Iriſh men, and well armed (meaning the Army raiſed by my Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> againſt <hi>Scotland</hi>) then of the manner how it ought to be done.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that every one ſhould indeavour to draw his owne freinds into that act, and at leaſt thoſe that did live in one Countrey with them, and when they had ſo done that there ſhould be a ſet day appointed, and every one in his own quarters ſhould riſe out that day and ſeize on all the Armes he could get in his countrey, and ſend to the Iriſh in the low Countreis, and <hi>Spaine,</hi> to let them know of the day and reſolution, ſo that they be over with them by that Day, or ſoone after with ſupplyes of Armes, and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition as they could, and this Day to be neere winter, ſo that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> could not be able to ſend forces into <hi>Ireland</hi> before <hi>May,</hi> and by that time there was no doubt to be made, but that they themſelves would be ſupplyed by the Iriſh beyond Seas, who he ſaid could not miſſe of help from either <hi>Spaine</hi> or the Pope; But that his reſolution was not in all things allowed. For firſt it was reſolved nothing ſhould be done untill firſt they had ſent to the Iriſh over Seas, to know their advice, and what hope of ſuccour they could give; for in them as they ſaid, all their hope of releife was; and they would have both their advice and reſolution, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any further proceedings more then to ſpeake to, and try the Gentlemen of the Kingdome, every one as he could convenietly, to ſee in caſe they would at any time grow to a Reſolution, what back and ſtrength they might truſt to. Then Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> told them that it was to no purpoſe to ſpend much time in ſpeaking to the Gentlemen, for there was no doubt to be made of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Iriſh, that they would be ready at any time, And that all the doubt was in the Gentlemen of the <hi>Pale,</hi> but he ſaid that for his owne part he was really aſſured when they had riſen out, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113789:4"/> 
                  <hi>Pale</hi> Gentlemen would not ſtay long after them, at leaſt that they would not oppoſe them in any thing but be Neuters, &amp; if in caſe they did, that they had men enough in the Kingdome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. Moreover he ſaid, that he had ſpoke to a great man (who then ſhould be nameles) that would not faile at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed day of riſing out to appeare and be ſeene in the Act, but that untill then he was ſworne not to reveale him. And that was all that was done at that meeting, onely that Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> ſhould the next Lent following, make a journey downe into the <hi>North</hi> to know what was done there, and that he alſo might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them what he had done, and ſo on parting Maſter <hi>Philip Rely</hi> and I did importune Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> for the knowledge of that great man that he ſpoke of, and on long intreaty, after bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us to new ſecrecy, not to diſcloſe him untill the day ſhould be appointed, he told it was the Lord of <hi>Mayo,</hi> who was very powerfull in command of men in thoſe parts of <hi>Conaght</hi> where-he lived, and that there was no doubt, to be made of him, no more then was of himſelfe, and ſo we parted.</p>
               <p>The next Lent following Maſter <hi>More</hi> according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe came to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and by reaſon it was the time of Aſſizes in ſeverall Counties, there he met onely with M. <hi>Rely,</hi> and nothing was then done, but all matters put off untill the May follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where we, or moſt of us, ſhould meet at <hi>Dublin,</hi> it then both being Parliament and Terme time; In the mean time there landed in <hi>Ireland</hi> one <hi>Neale O Neale,</hi> ſent by the Earle of <hi>Tyrone</hi> out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to ſpeak to thoſe Gentlemen of his name and kindred, to let them know that he had treated with Cardinall <hi>Richelieu</hi> for obtaining ſuccour to come for Irrland, and that he prevailed with the Cardinall, ſo that he was to have Armes, Munition and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from him, on demand to come for Ireland, and that he onely expected a convenient time to come away, and to deſire them to be in a readineſſe, and to procure all others whom they could to be ſo likewiſe, which meſſage did ſet forward the proceedings very much, ſo that Maſter <hi>More,</hi> Maſter <hi>Rely,</hi> my Brother and I, meeting the next day in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the ſame Meſſenger being there too, it was reſolved that he ſhould returne to the Earle into Spaine with their reſolution: which was that they would riſe out 12. or 14. dayes before or after Alhollantide, as they ſhould ſee cauſe, and that he ſhould not faile to be with them by that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113789:5"/> time; (there was a report at that time and before, that the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> was killed, which was not beleeved, by reaſon of many ſuch reports formarly which was found to be falſe) and ſo the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger departed with directions, that if the Earles death were true, he ſhould repaire into the Low-countries to Colonell <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> and acquaint him with his Comiſſion from the Earle (whereof it was thought he was not ignorant, and to ſee what he would adviſe, or could do himſelf therein, and returne an anſwer. But preſent after his departure the certainty of the Earles death was known, and on further reſolution it was agreed that an expreſſe Meſſenger ſhould be ſent to the Colonell to make all the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions known to him, and to returne ſpeedily with his anſwer, and ſo one <hi>Toole Connilly</hi> a Prieſt (as I think Pariſh Prieſt to Maſter <hi>More</hi>) was ſent away to Colonell <hi>O Neale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>interim</hi> there came ſeverall Letters and news out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to <hi>Dublin,</hi> of Proclamations againſt the Catholiques in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and alſo that the Army raiſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conveied into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and preſently after ſeverall Colonels and Captaines landed with directions to carry away thoſe men, amongſt whom Colonell <hi>Pluncket,</hi> Colonell <hi>Birne,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Brian O Neale</hi> came, but did not all come together, for Colonell <hi>Pluncket</hi> landed before my comming out of town, and the other two after: whereupon a great feare of ſuppreſſing Religion was conceived, and eſpecially by the Gentlemen of the Pale, and it was very common amongſt them, that it would be very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to ſuffer ſo many men to be conveied out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it being as it was ſaid very confidently reported, that the Scottiſh Army did threaten, never to lay down Armes, untill an uniformity of Religion were in the three Kingdoms, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion ſuppreſſed. And thereupon both Houſes of Parliament began to oppoſe their going, and the Houſes were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in opinion; ſome would have them go, others not; but what the definitive concluſion of the Houſes was touching that point, I cannot tell, for by leave from the Houſe of Lords I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted into the Countrey before the Prorogation: but before my departure I was informed by <hi>John Barnewall</hi> a Frier, that thoſe Gentlemen of the Pale, and ſome others (Members of the Houſe of Commons) had ſeverall meetings and conſultations how they might make ſtay of the Souldiers in the Kingdome, and likewiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113789:5"/> Arme them for the defence of the King (being then much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they were informed) and to prevent any attempt againſt Religion, for it was ſaid (but very ſecretly) that the King did in thoſe times ſay to Maſter <hi>Nicholas Plunket</hi> (one of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Committee then in <hi>England</hi>) that if they would ſtick to him, he would ſticke to them; this I heard (I think) from the ſaid <hi>John Barnewell,</hi> but in truth I am not ſure whether from him or no, but certaine I am, that he from whom I heard it, did confidently report it. And preſently after I departed into the Countrey, and Maſter <hi>O Rely</hi> being a Member of the Houſe of Commons ſtayed till the Prorogation, and on his coming into the Countrey ſent to me to meet him, and I came to his houſe, where he told me that he heard for certaine that the former narration of <hi>Barnewall</hi> to me (for I did acquaint him with it) was true, and that he heard it from ſeverall, there was alſo <hi>Emer Macmahone,</hi> (made privy formerly to all our proceedings) at Mr. <hi>O Relyes,</hi> lately come out of the place, where he met with the aforenamed <hi>John Barnewall,</hi> who told him as much as he formerly told me, and moreover that thoſe Collonells that lately came over, did proffer their ſervice and induſtry in that act, and ſo would raiſe their men under colour to convey them into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and then ſeize on the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and with the Armes there Arme their ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and have them ready for any action, that ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, but that they <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d not concluded any thing, becauſe they were not aſſured how the Gentlemen of the remote parts of the Kingdome (and eſpecially of <hi>Vlſter</hi>) would ſtand affected to that act, and that aſſurance of that doubt was all their impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; then we three began to think how we might aſſure them of the aſſiſtance and help of <hi>Vlſter</hi> Gentlemen: It was thought that one ſhould be ſent to them to acquaint them therewith, and they made choyſe of me to come, by reaſon, as they ſaid, that my wife was allyed to them, and their Countrey woman, and would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and truſt me ſooner then another of thoſe parts, they or moſt of them being of the <hi>Pale,</hi> and ſo (without as much as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne home) to furniſh my ſelfe for ſuch a journey, <hi>(volens nolens)</hi> they prevailed, or rather forced me to come to <hi>Dublin</hi> to conferre with thoſe Collonells, (and that was the laſt <hi>August</hi> was twelve-month) coming to Towne, I met Sir <hi>James Dillon</hi> accidentally before I came to my lodging, who was one of theſe Collonells,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113789:6"/> and after ſalutation he demanded of me where my lodging was, which when I told him, we parted. The next day being abroad about ſome other occaſions of mine owne in Towne I met him, (as he ſaid) comming to waite on me in my Chamber, but being a good way from it, he deſired me to goe to his owne Chamber being neere at hand, and then began to diſcourſe of the preſent ſufferings and afflictions of that Kingdome, and particularly in Religion, and how they were to expect no redreſſe, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>England</hi> intending, and the Scots reſolving never to lay downe Armes untill the Catholick Religion was ſuppreſſed, then he likewiſe began to lay downe what danger it would be to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo many able men (as were to goe with them) to depart the Kingdome in ſuch a time, neither (ſaith he) doth theſe other Gentlemen that are Collonells, and my ſelfe affect our owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate profit, ſo as to preferre it before the generall good of the Kingdome, and knowing that you are well affected thereunto, (and I hope, ſaid he, ready to put your helping hand to it on occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) I will let you know the reſolution of thoſe other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and mine, which is, we are ready to raiſe our men, and after to ſeize on the Caſtle where there is great ſtore of Armes, and arme our ſelves there; (this was the firſt motion that I ever heard, of taking the Caſtle, for it never came into our thoughts formerly nor am I perſwaded never would, if it had not proceeded from thoſe Collonells, who were the firſt mentioners and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers thereof, for ought knowne to me) and then be ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and reſiſt any danger, if the Gentry of the Kingdome like thereof and helpe us, for we of our ſelves neither are able nor will doe any thing therein without their aſſiſtance. I began ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the directions that were ſent with me, to approve of the Reſolution, &amp; alſo to let him know how ſure he might be of the aſſiſtance of thoſe of <hi>Vlſter,</hi> then he told me that for my more ſatisfaction, I ſhould conferre with the reſt of thoſe Collonells themſelves, as many as were privy to that action, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a place of meeting was appointed that afternoone; and at the time and place appointed I met Sir <hi>James</hi> himſelfe, Collonell <hi>Barne,</hi> and Collonell <hi>Plunket,</hi> and that former diſcourſe being renewed, they began to lay downe the obſtacles to that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and how they ſhould be redreſſed.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if there ſhould war enſue, how there ſhould be money had to pay the ſouldiers.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113789:6"/>
               <p>Secondly, how and where they ſhould procure ſuccour for forraigne parts.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, how to draw in the <hi>Pale</hi> Gentry.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, who ſhould undertake to ſurprize the Caſtle, and how it ſhould be done.</p>
               <p>To the firſt it was anſwered, that the Rents in the Kingdome every where, not having reſpect whoſe they ſhould be, due to the Lords and Gentry thereof, ſhould be collected to pay the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and moreover they might be ſure (my that there was no doubt to be made thereof) to procure money from the Pope, who gave ſeverall promiſes formerly to my Lord of <hi>Tyrone</hi> (in caſe he could make way to come into <hi>Ireland</hi>) to maintaine ſix thouſand men yeerely at his owne charge, and that notwithſtanding that my Lord of <hi>Tyrone</hi> was dead, yet that he would continue the ſame forwardnes now.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond it was anſwered by Collonell <hi>Birne,</hi> that helpe from abroad could not faile them, for (ſaid he) Collonell <hi>O Neale</hi> told me, that he had, or would procure in a readines, I doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member which of thoſe the Colonells ſpoke, or whether he ſpoke poſitive that Collonell <hi>O Neale</hi> had the Armes, or would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them,) Armes for ten thouſand men. And moreover (ſaid he) I make no great queſtion that if we ſend into <hi>Spayne</hi> we ſhall not miſſe of aid, for I being in <hi>London</hi> the laſt yeare, in the Scots trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, I was in conference with one of the Spaniſh Ambaſſadours there then, and talking of thoſe troubles then a foote, he ſaid, that if the Iriſh did then riſe ſo, and ſend into <hi>Spayne,</hi> their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers would be received under Canopies of gold; theſe laſt words he told me, and ſome one man that was preſent privately, whoſe name I cannot call to mind (neither well I remember whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſpake to them all or no,) then it was thought that when they were once in Arms for the defence of the Catholique cauſe, they would be ſuccoured by the Catholique Princes in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>To the third it was anſwered by Collonell <hi>Plunket,</hi> that he was as morrally certaine (for thoſe were his words) as he could be of any thing that the <hi>Pale</hi> Gentry would joyne with and aſſiſt them, for (ſaid he) I have ſpoke to ſeverall of them ſince my lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Kingdome, and I finde them very ready and willing withall, I have at <hi>London</hi> ſpoke to ſome of the Committees, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113789:7"/> particularly to my Lord of <hi>Gormonſtone</hi> to let them know this Reſolution, and they approved of it very well, and with all, they knew of the former conſultations by thoſe Gentry, told me by <hi>Barnewall.</hi> All this was not done at the firſt meeting, but at three or foure meetings, and ſo at the laſt meeting it was reſolved to the laſt doubt touching ſeizing the Caſtle, That Collonell <hi>Plunket</hi> and Collonell <hi>Birne</hi> ſhould undertake that taske, and they were named that firſt ſhould ſuccour them, that ſhould take the Caſtle with men preſently, namely Sir <hi>James Dillon</hi> who did undertake to be with them, within three (or at the moſt) foure dayes with one thouſand men, and ſo many more ſhould come to them out of the North, for thoſe two Collonells did not intend to uſe above one hundred men in the ſurprizall, whereof they were to have twenty good able Gentlemen; for they made account that having the Caſtle, they with the Artillery would Maſter the Towne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they were releived from the Countrey, and then there was a ſet day appointed for the execution thereof, that was the firſt of the enſuing <hi>October,</hi> this being the latter end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> or the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of <hi>September, Anno</hi> 1641. (I doe not know whither) and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhould make proviſion to riſe that day, and alſo ſeize on all the forts, garriſons, and other places, where they think, any Armes ſhould be, and in particular <hi>London-Derry,</hi> which ſhould be undertaken by thoſe of <hi>Vlſter,</hi> and becauſe there was a doubt made how all this could be done in ſo ſhort a time, they did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point that all that were there preſent ſhould not faile to meete againe there the twenty of <hi>September,</hi> to give an Accompt of all things, as well hopes as impediments, and if at that interveiw all things ſhould happen to be well that they goe forward, or if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, to prolong the Execution of it to a more convenient time, and ſo we parted, every man into the Countrey, about his owne taske: and I in my way home, came to Maſter <hi>O Relyes</hi> houſe, and there I received a letter from Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale,</hi> that his Lady was dead, and to be buried on the <hi>Sunday</hi> following, this being on the <hi>Saturday,</hi> and deſiring me in all kindnes to come to the buriall, and Maſter <hi>O Rely</hi> having received another letter to the ſame effect, would needes have me goe thither, (whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I was very unwilling, being weary, and withall not provided to goe to ſuch a meeting,) as well (ſaid he) to prevent any jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie from the Ladies freinds, as alſo to conferre with Sir <hi>Phelim</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113789:7"/> touching all theſe proceedings (for neither he nor I did ever ſpeak to Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> concerning thoſe matters before) but to his brother Mr. <hi>Tiloragh O Neale,</hi> &amp; comming thither, we found Capt. <hi>Bryan O Neale,</hi> lately come out of the low Countries, ſent over by Col. <hi>O Neale</hi> to ſpeake to, and provoke thoſe of <hi>Vlſter</hi> to riſe out into Armes, and that he would be with them on notice of their day; the ſame day, or ſoone after it; and it was asked of the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, what aide he could ſend or procure, being but a private Collonell, or where he could get any? He replyed that the ſaid Collonell told him, that hee had ſent to ſeverall places that Summer to demaund aide, and in particular to Cardinall <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheleiu</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> (to whom he had ſent twice that yeare) and had comfortable and very hopefull promiſes from them, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially from that Cardinall, on whom he thought the Collonell did moſt depend; ſo that there was no doubt to be made of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour from him, and eſpecially when they had riſen out, that it would be a meanes to the Cardinall to give aide; we did the more credit him in regard of the former treaty betweene the ſaid Cardinall and the Earle of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> (as formerly is ſaid) for my owne part, I did and doe beleeve that the Collonell doth depend on <hi>France</hi> for aide, more then on any other place, as well for theſe reaſons, as alſo, that <hi>Omer Macmahone</hi> formerly mentioned, told me that preſently after the Iſle of <hi>Rees</hi> enterprize (he being then in the Low Countreies) did heare for certaine that the Earl of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone,</hi> together with the Colonells, did ſend into <hi>France</hi> to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of <hi>France</hi> (that was the Generall of the French forces at the Iſle of <hi>Rees</hi>) to deale with him for procuring of aide, to come then for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he received in anſwer from the ſaid Marſhall, that he was moſt willing and ready to contribute his indeaveours for his furtherance therein, but that for the preſent he could not anſwer my Lords expectation, by reaſon that the King had wars then in <hi>Italy,</hi> which hee thought would be at an end within halfe a yeare, or little more, and then my Lord ſhould not doubt of any thing that he could doe for his aſſiſtance, but thoſe warres continued a great deale longer; ſo for that time that enterprize failed: and after the buriall was done, I gave thoſe Gentlemen knowledge of what I had done at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and how I was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thither, and then they began to thinke how to ſurprize <hi>London-Derry,</hi> they being neere it, but could not then agree in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113789:8"/> the manner, and ſo Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> deſired me to take his houſe in my way going to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and that I ſhould have a Reſolution to to carry with me touching <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and thereupon I parted home, but ſoone after came to <hi>Dublin,</hi> to the afore-appointed meeting with thoſe Colonells: But firſt, I tooke in my way Sir <hi>Phelim O Neales</hi> houſe, to be certaine what he had done; and his anſwer was, that he knew that matters could not be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution by the fift of <hi>October,</hi> as was appointed, and that they would make another longer day for it, and that he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the taking of <hi>London-Derry</hi> by that day; and ſo I came to <hi>Dublin,</hi> to give an account of that was done, and alſo know what further ſhould be done: I was not two houres in my lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging when Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> came to me (who knew of what was done by thoſe Colonells formerly by Coll. <hi>Birne,</hi> and told me that the Meſſenger ſent to Colonell <hi>Neale</hi> was come with anſwer, deſiring us not to delay any time in riſing out, and to let him know of that day before hand, and that hee would not faile to be with us within fourteene dayes of that day with good aide, alſo deſiring us by any meanes to ſeaze the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi> if we could, for he heard that there was great proviſion in it for warre, and Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> moreover ſaid, that time was not to be over-ſlipped, and deſired me to be very preſſing with the Colonells to goe on in their reſolution, but on meeting with them they were fallen from their former reſolution, becauſe thoſe of the Pale would doe nothing therein firſt, but when it was done, they would not faile to aſſiſt, as Collonell <hi>Plunket</hi> did affirme, and ſo on ſeverall meetings, it was reſolved on by them to deſiſt from that enterprize for that time, and to expect a more convenient time; but before that their reſolution, Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale,</hi> and the aforeſaid Capt. <hi>Brian O Neale</hi> followed me to <hi>Dublin</hi> (as they ſaid) to aſſiſt and adviſe me how to proceede with that Colonell (but neither they nor Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> would be ſeene therein them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe Gentlemen, but would meete me privately, and know what was done at every meeting, alleadging for excuſe, that I being firſt imployed in that matter, it would not be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that they ſhould be ſeene in it; and moreover they would not be knowne to me to be in Towne, but by a few of their friends, untill they were in a manner ready to depart, at leaſt, as long as I was in Towne, for I left them there, but when I made them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113789:8"/> with their determination of deſiſting from that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, they thought it convenient that we ſhould meete with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Moore,</hi> and Collonell <hi>Birne,</hi> to ſee what was further to be done concerning the former intention of their owne, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly we did ſend to them, that they ſhould meete us, and at that meeting, where were onely Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> Colonell <hi>Birne,</hi> Captaine <hi>Neale,</hi> and my ſelfe: after long debate, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that we, with all thoſe that were of our faction ſhould goe on with that determination, that was formerly in May con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, to wit, to riſe out, and moreover to ſeize on the Caſtle, (as the Colonells were purpoſed) for if it were not for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the adviſe ſent by Colonell <hi>Neale</hi> we would never venture to ſurprize it, neither was it ever thought on in all the meetings and reſolutions betweene us, before that thoſe Colonels did reſolve on it, but by reaſon that the other Gentlemen that were private to their proceedings were not preſent, the certainty of the time, and the manner how to execute it, were put off to a further meeting in the Country; and this was reſolved in <hi>Dublin</hi> on the Saturday at night, being the 26. or 27. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> and that meeting was appointed on the Saturday following at Mr. Collo. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>hones</hi> houſe in <hi>Far<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> in the County of <hi>Monaghan,</hi> but by reaſon that at the meeting the Gentlemen of <hi>Limſter</hi> could not be preſent, conſidering the remoteneſſe of the place from them, it was thought fit that Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> ſhould there meete to receive the finall reſolution, and ſhould acquaint them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and in the meane time Col. <hi>Birne,</hi> who had undertaken for Col. <hi>Plunket,</hi> ſhould informe them all of the intention concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and diſpoſe them in a readineſſe againſt that day that ſhould be appointed, and thereupon we all left the Towne, onely Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> ſtaide about ſome other his private occaſions, but did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his being there at that day.</p>
               <p>On the Saturday I came to Mr. <hi>Macmahones</hi> houſe, there meet onely Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Macmahone</hi> himſelfe, Captaine <hi>Neale, Emer Macmahone,</hi> and my ſelfe (and thither the ſame day came that Meſſenger that was ſent to Coll. <hi>Neale,</hi> and did report the Colonells anſwers and advice <hi>verbatim,</hi> as I have formerly repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Mr. <hi>Moore</hi>) and by reaſon that Sir. <hi>Phelim</hi> his brother, or Mr. <hi>Philip O Rely</hi> that were deſired to meete, did not meete, we ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied that night to expect them; and that night I received a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113789:9"/> Letter from Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> intteating us by any meanes not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him untill the Munday following, for he had not, nor could diſpatch ſome occaſions neerely concerning him, but whatſoever came of them, he would not faile on the Munday. And the next day after receipt of the Letter, being Sunday (by Mr. <hi>Moores</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) we departed from Mr. Coll. <hi>Macmahones</hi> houſe, (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent (as he ſaid) the ſuſpition of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> living thereabouts to <hi>Louroſſe,</hi> in the County of <hi>Ardmaugh</hi> to Mr. <hi>Torilagh O Neales</hi> houſe, not Sir <hi>Phelims</hi> brother, but Son to Mr. <hi>Henry O Neale</hi> of the <hi>Fues,</hi> Son in Law to Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> and left word that if Sir <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim,</hi> or any of thoſe other Gentlemen did come in the meane time they ſhould follow us thither (whether onely went Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> Captaine <hi>O Neale,</hi> and my ſelfe) and there we expected untill the Tueſday ſubſequent, before any of thoſe did come: On the Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day came Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> and Mr. <hi>Emer Macmahone,</hi> all the reſt fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come, Mr. Collonell <hi>Macmahons</hi> wife was dead the night before, which was the cauſe that he was not there, but I gave his aſſent to what ſhould be concluded to joyne therein, and execute what ſhould be appointed him, and then we five, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> Captaine <hi>O Neale, Emer Macmahone,</hi> and my ſelfe, aſſuring our ſelves that thoſe Gentlemen abſent would both allow and joyne to what we ſhould determine, did grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a finall reſolution, grounding all, or moſt part of our hope and confidence on the ſuccour from Collonell <hi>Neale,</hi> to ſeize on the Caſtle, and riſe out all in one day, and the day was appointed on the 23. of that month, this being the fift day of <hi>October,</hi> having regard therein to the day of the weeke whereon that day did fall, which was the Saturday, being the Market day, on wich day there would be leſſe notice taken of people up and downe the ſtreets: Then began a queſtion who ſhould be deputed for the ſurprizall of the Caſtle, and then Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> ſaid he would be one of them himſelf, and that Coll. <hi>Birne</hi> ſhould be another, and what other Gentlemen of <hi>Leinſter</hi> they could procure to joyne with them, and ſeeing the Caſtle had two gates, the one the great, and the other the little gate, going downe to my Lord Leiutenants Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, hard by which Stable without the Caſtle was the ſtote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe for Armes, they of <hi>Leinſter</hi> would undertake one Gate, and that ſhould be the little Gate, and the great Gate ſhould be undertaken by thoſe at <hi>Vlſter,</hi> (and ſaid he) of neceſſity one of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113789:9"/> you both (meaning Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> &amp; me) muſt be there for the better countenance of that matter, it being the glory of all our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; his ſpeeches were well liked of all preſent, but Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> would be exempted from that imployment, and ſo would I; but then all of them ſet on me, deſiring me to be one; alleadging for reaſon that their proceedings &amp; reſolutions were very honourable and glorious, being for Religion, and for to procure more liberty for their Countrey, as did (ſaid they) of late <hi>Scotland;</hi> and that in taking the Caſtle conſiſted all the glory and honour of the ſaid Action, all which ſhould be attributed to them that ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed therein, and ſo by conſequence all or moſt part to me, being (as they ſaid) the cheife in that enterprize; and moreover Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> ſaid, that he would endeavour to take or procure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to take <hi>London-Derry</hi> the ſame day, and if he ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that place would not be taken. With theſe and many other perſwaſions they obtained my conſent, and then the Captain of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe. We began then to conſider what number ſhould be imployed in that act, and they concluded on two hundred men, a hundred from each Province, for thoſe Gates which they ſeize on, of which number Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale</hi> ſhould ſend forty with an able ſufficient Gentleman to conduct them; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Captaine <hi>Neale</hi> twenty, Maſter Collonell <hi>Macmahone</hi> ten, Maſter <hi>O Rely</hi> ten more, and I ſhould bring twenty. Then began a doubt how they ſhould raiſe thoſe men, and convey them to <hi>Dublin</hi> without ſuſpition; and it was anſwered, that under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of carrying them to thoſe Colonels that were conveying Souldiers out of the Kingdome, it might ſafely be done; and to that purpoſe Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale,</hi> Maſter <hi>More,</hi> and the Captaine had ſeverall blanke Patents with deputations to make Captains to thoſe Colonells, which they ſent to thoſe Gentlemen, that ſhould ſend men to <hi>Dublin,</hi> for the more colour; Then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of what was to be done in the Countrey that day, and it was reſolved that every one privie to that matter, in every part of the Kingdom, ſhould riſe out that day, and ſeize on all the Forts and Armes in the ſeverall Counties, to make all the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen priſoners the more to aſſure themſelves againſt any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe fortune, and not to kill any but where of neceſſity they ſhould be forced thereunto by oppoſition (which thoſe that were appointed for taking the Caſtle ſhould obſerve) and in particular
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113789:10"/> they bent all their aime in <hi>Vlſter</hi> to take that day <hi>London-Derry,</hi> which Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> did undertake; <hi>Knockfergus,</hi> which they thought Sir <hi>Henry O Neales</hi> brother would doe, and to that end Sir <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lims</hi> Brother <hi>Terilaugh O Neale</hi> ſhould be ſent to them; and the Nurie, which ſhould be undertaken by Sir <hi>Margeriaſſe,</hi> and his Brothers, for whom Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> (in regard they were his brothers in law, his deceaſed Lady being their Siſter) did undertake. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over it was agreed, that Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> Maſter <hi>O Rely,</hi> Maſter <hi>Coll. Macmahone,</hi> and my brother ſhould, with all ſpeed they could, after that day raiſe all the forces they could and follow us to <hi>Dublin,</hi> both to arme the men and ſuccour us, and defend and garriſon the Towne and Caſtle, and likewiſe Maſter <hi>More</hi> ſhould appoint <hi>Leinſter</hi>-Gentlemen to ſend like ſupply of men. All which I was by their appointment to informe Maſter <hi>O Rely,</hi> I being next him, together with what he was to doe for his own part. Then there was feare of the Scots conceived, that they would preſently oppoſe themſelves, and that would make the matter more difficult; to avoide which danger it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to meddle with them or any thing belonging to them, and to demeane our ſelves towards them as if they were of us, which we thought would pacify them from making any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if the Scots would not accept of that offer of Amity, but would oppoſe us, we were in good hope to cauſe a ſtirre in Scotland, that might divert them from us. And I beleeve the ground for that hope was, that two yeares before in or about the beginning of the Scots troubles, my Lord of <hi>Tyrone</hi> ſent one <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilagh O Neale</hi> (a Preiſt) out of <hi>Spayne</hi> (and this I take it was the time that he was in Treaty with Cardinall <hi>Richelieu</hi>) to my Lord of <hi>Argyle,</hi> to treat with him for help from my Lord, for him to come into Ireland, and as was ſaide for a marriage, betweene the ſaide Earle and my Lord of <hi>Argyles</hi> daughter (or Siſter I know not which) and this meſſenger tooke Ireland in his way thither, with whom Maſter <hi>Terilagh O Neale,</hi> Sir <hi>Phelims</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had conference, from whom this relation was had. That ſaid meſſenger went into <hi>Scotland</hi> as I did heare from the ſaid Maſter <hi>Neale,</hi> or from <hi>Emer Macmahone</hi> afore named, I know not from which of them; but what he did there I could never heare, by reaſon that my Lord of <hi>Tyrone</hi> was preſently after kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; they were the more confirmed therein, hearing that my Lord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113789:10"/> of <hi>Argyle</hi> did ſay (neare on the ſame time as I gueſſe, and when the Army was raiſed in Ireland as I thinke) to a great Lady in <hi>Scotland;</hi> I know not her name, but did heare that ſhe was much imbarked in the troubles of that Kingdome, then; ſhe queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how they could ſubſiſt againſt the two Kingdomes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and Ireland, that if the King did endeavour to ſtirre Ireland againſt them, he would kindle ſuch a fire in Ireland as would hardly or never be quenched; And moreover we knew my Lord to be powerfull with the Ilanders, or Red-ſhankes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> whom we judged would be prone and ready to ſuch Actions, they for the moſt part being deſcended out of Ireland, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Iriſh language and manners ſtill; and ſo we parted, the next day being Wedneſday, from <hi>Lough Roſſe,</hi> every man about his owne taske; and ſo when I came home I acquainted my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all that was done, and what they had appointed him to doe, and did likewiſe (according as they appointed me) ſend to Maſter <hi>O Rely</hi> to let him know as much. And the eighteenth of the ſame moneth I began my journey to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and when I came to <hi>Dublin</hi> being the day before the appointed day of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that reſolution in execution there, I met with Captaine <hi>Con O Neale</hi> ſent out of the Low-Countryes by Colonell <hi>O Neale,</hi> (who came after the meſſenger ſent by us formerly to the ſaide Colonell, and was by him diſpatched with his Anſwer) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us in our reſolution, and to ſpeedy performance, with aſſurance of ſuccours, which he ſaid would not fail on the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonells behalfe; And for the more certainty of helpe from him, and to aſſure us that the Colonell had good hopes to procure aide from others, he ſaid that it was he himſelf that was imploied from him to Card. <hi>Richelieu</hi> twice that Summer, who gave them very faire promiſes to anſwer the Colonells expectation, with which he ſaid that the ſaid Colonell and himſelfe were really aſſured of the Cardinalls aide, and that he was likewiſe commanded by the Collonell upon our Reſolution of the day to give notice thereof to him, and that he would be within foureteene dayes over with us with aide; but he the ſaid <hi>Con O Neale</hi> landing 9. or 10. dayes before, and meeting with Captaine <hi>Brian O Neale,</hi> who made him acquainted with what was reſolved, he did write all the matter to Colonell <hi>O Neale;</hi> ſo as he was ſure of his ſpeedy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. And that Evening he and I came to meete the other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113789:11"/> and there we met Maſter <hi>Moore,</hi> Collonell <hi>Birne,</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Plunket,</hi> Captaine <hi>Fox,</hi> and another <hi>Leinſter</hi>-Gentleman, a Captaine I thinke of the <hi>Birnes,</hi> but I am not ſure wheiher a <hi>Birne</hi> or a <hi>Toole,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Birgan O Neale;</hi> and taking an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of thoſe that ſhould have beene there, it was founde that Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale</hi> and Maſter <hi>Collo Macmahone,</hi> did faile of ſending their men, and Colonell <hi>Birne</hi> did miſſe Sir <hi>Mergan Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanagh</hi> that had promiſed him to be there, but he ſaid he was ſure he would not fail to be that night or the next morning in Town, and of the two hundred men that were appointed, there were onely eighty preſent, yet notwithſtanding they were reſolved to goe on in their Reſolution, and all the difference was at what time of the day they ſhould ſet on the Caſtle, and after ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it was reſolved in the afternoone, and the rather hoping to meete the Councell there then; for they ſaide, if they ſhould take the Caſtle, and be inforced by any extreamity for not receiving timely ſuccour out of the Countrey, having them, they could not want; and ſo parted that night, but to meete in the morning to ſee further what was to be done; and immediately thereon I came to my Chamber, and about nine of the clock Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> and Captaine <hi>Fox</hi> came to me and told me that all was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that the City was in Armes, and the Gates ſhut up, and ſo departed from me, and what became of them, or of the reſt I know not, but think that they eſcaped, yet how or at what time I doe not know, becauſe I my ſelfe was taken that morning.</p>
               <p>After a deliberate reading and rumination of this account (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Macquir</hi>) I ſhall deſire the Reader to be diſtinct in theſe particular conſiderations. Firſt, I would have him obſerve here the principall Agents in this deſperate Aſſaſſination. Secondly, I would have notice taken what the end and pretences were which moved, and enraged theſe Agents. Thirdly, what the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and contingencies were which made that very ſeaſon pitcht upon for action. Fourthly, what the ſtratagems and policies were which attended their enterprize. Fiftly To what degrees of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty they did at laſt arrive. Theſe particulars being truely and cleerely laid open, together with ſome other additionall eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the like authority, concluſions will iſſue of themſelves, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting us with the cauſes of all our miſeries, and amounting to no leſſe then what I have already premiſed and preſumed.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113789:11"/>1. Firſt therefore we ſee here a difference is to be noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the moſt eminent plotters, and the moſt violent execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of this miſcheife: the Lord <hi>Macquir</hi> gives a good relation of the executours, but not being acquainted with the conſpiracy it ſelfe, till it had beene matured by others, and was communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him by <hi>Roger Moore,</hi> about nine moneths before the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eruption; He ſaies nothing thereof; but tis plaine, that theſe Councells were laid long before by the Popiſh Clergy: for by the connivence of our Governours in Ireland, that Countrey had its Titular Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Vicar-generals, Provincial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories, Eccleſiaſticall Deanes, Abbotts, Priors, Monkes, Nunns, Jeſuits, Preiſts, and Fryars without number, beſides all Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall Officers, and as well in Townes as in the Countrey had free uſe of the Maſſe. Dr. Jones had it from the mouth of a Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſcan, that before the diſmall day of October, there was a great meeting at a religious houſe in Weſtmeath of the Romiſh Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and ſome others, whereat the queſtion was debated, what courſe ſhould be taken with the Engliſh, and how the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State ſhould be new moulded. And in <hi>May</hi> 1642. there was a generall congregation held at <hi>Kilkenney</hi> wherein the Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> was annexed to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the State made no leſſe in effect then purely Democraticall: and one Act was paſſed for ſending Embaſſadours in behalfe of the whole Kingdome to the Pope, the Emperour, the King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spayne,</hi> and thoſe to be of the Church Prelates, with one of the Nobility and a Lawyer: Moreover all the acts of <hi>Kilkenney</hi> were onely ſubſcribed by three Archbiſhops, ſixe Biſhops, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty others either of the Clergy, or ſome holy orders, or officers belonging to the Hierarchy: whereby it appeares that the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Gentry, and Commonalty of Ireland (though the adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and active part of the warre be left to them) have as yet but very little or no ſhare in the directive or gubernative part; much leſſe had they whilſt the matter was but in conſultation; Beſides, we know the Eccleſiaſticks, were ranged into fit ſtations, and as there was a juſt number appointed to attend at home for managing of buſineſſe in Ireland, ſo there was as vaſt a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſtributed abroade into the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other Courts of <hi>Europe</hi> for forraigne Agency and correſpondency. Wherefore if the Apoſtolick ſea ever did lively repreſent the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomles
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113789:12"/> pit reeking forth thick fumes, or darkening the skye with ſwarmes of odious Locuſts, doubtleſſe at this time by the emiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo many Regulars and Seculars, upon ſuch confounding meſſages, it did verify and explaine that dimme prediction.</p>
               <p>Well: but after the Jeſuits and Preiſts had beene long in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration about this woefull tragedy, at laſt the troubles of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have occaſioned a Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> and raiſed an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Papiſts in Ireland; and now all advantages concurring, ſuch of the Lords &amp; Gentry, as are moſt apt for innovation are to be ſollicited, and rightly inſtructed how to draw in other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current partyes in all the foure ſeverall Provinces.</p>
               <p>The common people are not to be truſted with the knowledge of any thing till the very night it ſelfe approaches; nay the very Gentry themſelves, except ſome few choſen ones, are not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this ſecret till all things are ready for execution: the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Maſſe, and of Confeſſion (which are made Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brages to draw the multitude together, and myſterious attractives to engage in this helliſh ſacrifice,) are not to be ſolemnized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day appointed. There was feare that the multitude could not be prepared without diſcovery; but there was no feare that the multitude would not conſent without preparation. At a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore in <hi>Dublin</hi> 8 monthes at leaſt before this infamous October, when one of the Conſpiratours adviſed to imploy time in ſpeaking to, and trying the Gentry of Ireland, till advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could be received from the other undertakers beyond the ſeas: Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> replyed, that it was to no purpoſe to ſpende much time in ſpeaking to the Gentry; for there was no doubt to be made of the Iriſh, that they would be ready at any time; but all the doubt was in the Gentry of the <hi>Pale.</hi> Howſoever for his part his affirmation was that he was really aſſured, when the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh were up, the <hi>Pale</hi> Gentry would not ſtay long after. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeded alſo to intreate that the Lord of <hi>Maye</hi> (who was very powerfull in command of men in thoſe parts of <hi>Connaught</hi> wherein he lived) had beene ſpoken to by himſelfe, and that his conſent was granted, yet not without an oath for concealement of the ſame. But I will goe on with the Lord <hi>Macquir,</hi> to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the principal Lay-conjuratours who were not onely taken in by the Eccleſiaſticks for meere action, but were alſo admitted to ſome part of the contrivance at leaſt nine monthes before; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113789:12"/> we ſhall ſee ſome uſe may be made of the ſame. The firſt inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in, is <hi>Roger Moore,</hi> alias <hi>Roei Morace</hi> of the family of the <hi>Moraces</hi> of <hi>Leix</hi> in <hi>Lemſter,</hi> which County together with the Territories of <hi>Offali</hi> were eſcheated to the Crown by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and were planted with Engliſh in the Raigne of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Nevertheleſſe alſo the father of this <hi>Roei</hi> being civill and of peaceable diſpoſition, though a Papiſt, was by Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> cheriſht and ſufficiently provided for by a grant of faire and large poſſeſſions in the County of <hi>Keldare</hi> and <hi>Meath</hi> to him and his heires in fee, and the ſame did deſcend to this <hi>Roei.</hi> Here was Juſtice done long ſince by a Popiſh Queene to his dammage, here is grace ſhewed lately by a Proteſtant Queene to his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: what pretence of quarrell therefore can this afford to <hi>R. Moore</hi> for Papiſts againſt Proteſtants, or for former times againſt latter? The Lord <hi>Macqueir</hi> himſelfe, and his family may next take place; and we muſt take knowledge, that Sir <hi>Conor Ro. Macqueir</hi> his Grandfather was diveſted of the dignity of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queir,</hi> and the County of <hi>Termanagh,</hi> and unable to right him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, was reinſtated by the aide of the Engliſh, after which alſo he had not onely the <hi>Barony</hi> of <hi>Maghere ſtaffana,</hi> but alſo a yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly penſion for life granted out of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> by King <hi>James.</hi> And not long ſince <hi>Bryan</hi> the Sonne of Sir <hi>Connor,</hi> and father of this Lord, obtained a Patent from King <hi>Charles</hi> of the Barony of <hi>Eviskillim;</hi> if theſe offices be accounted diſobligations or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Iriſh againſt the Engliſh, or ſtirre up Papiſts againſt Proteſtants, certainely either the Iriſh differ from other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Popery differs from other Religions, or elſe the nature of ingratitude muſt needs be changed from what it was.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip O Rely</hi> comes now in view; and his Father Captaine <hi>Hugh Mac-ſhane O Rely</hi> had from King <hi>James</hi> a grant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation in fee of a faire eſtate in Lands, lying within the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Oavan,</hi> one of the eſcheated Counties of <hi>Vlſter.</hi> Of all the Rebels none ſcarſe ever did purſue the Engliſh and the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion more perfidiouſly, and deſperately, then this <hi>Philip</hi> and his family, yet here is to be ſeene what it coſt King <hi>James</hi> to incenſe him ſo deeply againſt us.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale,</hi> and his brother <hi>Torilah</hi> may preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after the <hi>O Relies;</hi> and theſe in their minority being left Orphans by <hi>Oge O Neal</hi> their father, were liberally bred up in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113789:13"/> learning, and carefully recommended by our State to the tuition of the Lord <hi>Calfield,</hi> and when they had attained to full yeares, their fathers inheritance with ſome additions was ſettled upon them. Yet 'tis conjecturable that for as much as the Province of <hi>Vlſter</hi> did eſcheat by the ſeverall treaſons and attaindors of the Earles, <hi>Tyrone, Tyrconell,</hi> and others, if <hi>Tyrone</hi> had againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored himſelfe according to the deſigne of theſe <hi>O Neales,</hi> the titles and poſſeſſions of this Family in <hi>Vlſter</hi> would have been ſhrewdly ſhaken, or at leaſt their power ecclipſd. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the <hi>O Neales</hi> now for ſuch offences as theſe, butcher a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Engliſh, and for their firſt ſacrifice ſlay the yong Lord <hi>Calfield</hi> their old Guardians ſon, and yet it muſt paſſe by the laws of Popery for a very faire, equitable, and gratefull retaliation. Colonell <hi>Mac-Mahon</hi> and his Family next in order, never could complaine of any moleſtation, or diſinheriſon by Engliſh plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, but all the <hi>Mac-Mahons</hi> of <hi>Farny</hi> and their chiefe had been extirpated by the <hi>O Neales,</hi> if the power of the Engliſh had not ſupported, and preſerved them. Sure ſuch meritorious obligations upon any other then either Iriſh, or Catholicks, would have procured ſome other acknowledgement. We may now conclude with Sir <hi>Con. Mageniis</hi> and his brethren, and Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> his Father; and 'tis apparant, that upon the ſettlement of <hi>Vlſter,</hi> though he was in actuall rebellion with the Earle of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone,</hi> whoſe daughter he had married, yet he obtained from King <hi>Iames</hi> a grant and confirmation of the territory of <hi>Ireagle</hi> in the County of <hi>Doune</hi> to himſelfe and his heires in fee. Had an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, or Mahometan been ſo treated, we may well expect he would have ſtudied ſome other requitall then the totall extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe which ſo treated him, or he would have thought ſomething elſe had appertained to gratitude beſides murther and revenge. I thus ranke theſe conſpiratours by themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their taske was domeſticall, and moſt of them were of <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> and therefore policy required that where the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty was, moſt induſtry was to be uſed. For 'tis to be noted, that in Munſter, and in Conaght, where the Engliſh were thinner planted, and leſſe fortified, there was not that feare of oppoſition as in Vlſter and Lemſter, where the Scots and Engliſh were clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer embodied, and ſurer garriſond, but eſpecially neare Dublin where the Seate of Juſtice was, and the five adjacent Counties,
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
